Stack ranking is organizational cancer.
This is Bryan Cantrill. He was a
distinguished engineer at the original
Sun Microsystems and I asked him about
everything he learned over his 30-year
career.
Performance review is not about you
performing better. It's about us
measuring your performance. He had
interesting stories from competing with
Jeff Bezos. He is not merely a predator.
He is an apex predator in capitalist.
This is what makes him so good. To
stories from when he started his own
company Oxide. You go to hang up on a
VC, they'll be like, "Wait, wait, wait,
wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait,
wait, wait." I was like, "Oh, okay." And
he even let me grill him about his past.
You raise this long thing and you reply
with just a few words. You say, "Have
you ever kissed a girl?" We actually, I
mean, this is dark, but we
Here's the full episode.
You know, your career started at Sun
Microsystems and that's kind of a
legendary company. It was It was before
my time. What was the industry like when
you first entered it? Was there a FAANG
equivalents at the time? What was Sun
Microsystems like? What were the other
companies like?
>> Yeah, you know, it's kind of funny cuz
there's always been like a FAANG kind of
equivalent, you know, in the In the
'60s, it was called the bunch.
Burroughs, Univac, NCR, Control Data,
and Honeywell were the were were the
bunch. It was IBM and the bunch.
So, they
For kind of every era, there's always,
you know, some hot group, some some
growing sector. Um and in my day though,
so things were I I mean, I think in a
bit of a divot. So, I graduated in '96.
So, I was really interviewing in '95.
And there was there was for sure
on-campus interviews happening. But,
they
Microsoft was very dominant in that era.
And I definitely knew I was not going to
go to Microsoft as a kind of a point of
principle.
Um Why was that? Oh, I I view Bill Gates
robbed me of my childhood. Microsoft had
such garbage. I mean they really did. Um
In what sense? In their their operating
system was you know I I came up in the
personal computer era. So I I came up in
the 80s and it wasn't until uh you know
I I went to to university in 1992
and it wasn't um
you know I had just been accustomed to
kind of like
garbage on the computer. It's like it's
garbage in a way that is kind of
unfathomable. Now DOS itself the disk
operating system from Microsoft had no
memory protection whatsoever. So if an
application misbehaved the machine would
just reboot.
And this is this just became like part
of life is like the machines reboot. You
got to boy you got to save your work
because you'd be in WordPerfect or
WordStar whatever. This is why I sound
like a true like living fossil. I feel
like I'm I'm relaying like coming across
the Oregon Trail or something. But the
you'd be in your word processor you know
working on your English paper and all of
a sudden the machine would reboot. And
the and I just that that was just that
was life. And you hope you saved it. You
hope you had a hard copy.
And it was only when I got to college
that I realized like wait a minute hold
on there's there's actually something
called there's memory protection in the
microprocessor. And for much of my
adolescence there had been memory
protection present. And it DOS didn't
use it at all. And the and Windows used
it I mean with Windows it gets
complicated. But the answer the the
short answer is Windows didn't use it
either. And uh so it wasn't until I I
got to like Unix on a workstation and I
just remember being like you know 18
years old and having like having a a
command line shell up in one window
having an FTP to wuarchive downloading
some like EGA game that I'd want to go
play back in my dorm in another window
having something else going on in a
third window having a compile in a
fourth window and having this happen
magically concurrently was just
mind-bending. It's like, how is this
even possible? I mean, it again, it it
sounds and it's and I I I appreciate how
old this sounds, but but this is what it
was. And the then looking back, I'm
like, why do I have garbage from
Microsoft? And it's Microsoft was just
not an operating system company. They
were the dominant operating system
provider, but it but in their DNA, the
most fundamental, like the nucleotide
base pairs of Microsoft are compilers.
They were a compiler company, not an
operating systems company.
And Apple was, you know, Apple what was
Apple at that time? I mean, Apple had
this is long fired Steve Jobs. This is
the the the the Apple was kind of the
the Mac was really honestly not that
much better. It was like cleaner, but
also didn't make use of memory
protection.
So, this is just like unconscionable to
me, and there was just and this is like
aside from all the bad behavior from
Microsoft, and there was plenty of bad
behavior from Microsoft. Microsoft was
very anti-competitive. And, you know,
the findings of fact in the Netscape
case, you know,
years later would be just very
underhanded, very
wanting to like to it was not a company
that had the best technology. It was a
company that that that jockeyed for
position and then would kind of abuse
its position. What's the TLDR of that
that abuse?
So, what Microsoft would do, and this is
a pattern you would see repeated since,
but what Microsoft would do is they
would announce, you know, you have a
promising company that has something
that that is that's
that's a application that people might
use, they would announce that it's going
to become a forthcoming feature of the
operating system.
And then, but as it turns out, it then
it wouldn't show up. It was vaporware.
Uh the the term vaporware, I think if it
didn't originate with Microsoft,
Microsoft definitely perfected the art
of vaporware, of announcing something
that that didn't exist. And
they were kind of dominant with this
mediocrity. Now, to their credit, they
also when they went and for so for
example, Microsoft Word, which I mean um
still exists, but WordPerfect was the
really the dominant word processor,
WordPerfect and WordStar.
But, Microsoft Word was very bad, and to
their credit, it would get better over
time and ultimately supplanted uh
WordPerfect in part because they started
bundling it with the operating system.
So, they they were very deeply
anticompetitive, and that's not like an
opinion, that's like a that's like a
judicial finding of fact. That's a Judge
Alsup finding of fact. Um and the um and
that changed a lot when Gates I mean
Gates when he hit middle age, that
company changed a bunch and after the
antitrust case in the late '90s. But, I
was not going to work for Microsoft. I
saw in
your goodbye post for from Sun
Microsystems. When you were leaving the
company, you wrote a public post, and
you said that uh you
when you joined the company and you
interviewed, you only knew two things.
That you one, you wanted to work on an
operating system kernel development, and
two is that you didn't particularly want
to work for Sun.
But, it looks like you had an amazing
time. So, what what flipped the switch
from going from I don't want to work
here to I love working here? So, the
when I I had kind of talked with other
groups at Sun, and I just like the
people I dealt with at Sun were um
fine, but just not where it didn't feel
energizing.
And uh and especially PBN did not feel
Um and I you know, I was kind of
accustomed to being the youngest person
in a group, but you know, you don't want
to be completely by your lonesome. You
would you want to feel like there are
other people that have that kind of that
same shared passion. And uh when I met
Kevin Clark and Jeff Bonwick, um it was
like a bolt of lightning. Um those two
were um were uh energized, passionate,
really they they saw all of the same
things that I saw in terms of the
potential for operating systems to be
innovative and were and wanted to go
like rip out broken code and replace it
with with beautiful code and all that
that same verve um, that that I felt um,
and yeah, it was it was absolutely
meeting those two. You're just like,
okay, I I I there are I am going to work
for Sun. I remember actually very
vividly coming back from that trip being
like, oh my god, I'm going to go work
for Sun. If they make
they're going to make me an offer and
I'm absolutely going to go work there. I
saw that eventually you grew to a
distinguished engineer there. What was
the career ladder like? It'd be
interesting to know where the kind of
member of technical staff, staff
engineer, senior staff engineer,
distinguished engineer comes from. Um,
I think it might come from Sun. I think
it's possible that Sun is the
originating company. It's also possible
from Xerox PARC. You have to kind of
take it apart where and I actually
remember when I you know, I had
interacted with some folks at Sun and
they'd give me a business card and I
remember like coming out to Sun being
like and not really knowing what my rank
was and I'm like because I I was going
to make business cards. I'm like, what?
I'm an engineer and I'm on staff. So I
like I think I'm a staff engineer. So
and and you know, I kind of go to make
business cards and then I kind of like
didn't didn't complete submission on the
form or whatever and then of course it
wasn't that long afterwards I was like,
oh wait a minute. That was like that
would have been like saying I had got
tenure. Like I definitely not a staff
engineer. I'm a member of technical
staff.
Um, I was an MTS three. So the there was
the uh, you would kind of climb up
through those ranks and then to to staff
engineer, senior staff engineer,
distinguished engineer and And three was
the start of the good No, I mean it's
supposed I think it did start at MTS
one. Um, no, most college hires would
start at MTS two. Um, but they um, but I
I was an unusual college hire in a lot
of ways. Interesting. So they brought
you on two levels deep as a new grad.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, that's right. Um, I
mean I'd had a lot I um, so Sun was
actually not the first company I worked
for. I worked for a company called QNX
in Canada. Um, and I'd done kernel
development there. So, I'd done um, OS
development at at QNX for for two
summers. Um, and I'd done some actually
some work that I was that I still think
is actually I love that. I love working
for QNX. I love being in Canada.
Uh, and really and and I
I had decided I didn't want to go back
to QNX professionally that I that I did
want The other The other thing I would
say is I decided that I wanted to come
out to Silicon Valley. I I did not want
to be I'd gone to school in the
Northeast, had worked in Canada, but I
really wanted to come out to Silicon
Valley.
I see. So, then when you when you look
at your journey growing from I guess
this MTS3 to up to where you grew, like
if you were to break down that I guess
the story behind that growth and kind of
what are the highlights that that stuck
out to you that made you grow? Yeah, so
I mean, I was not
I was very much not focused on my my my
grade, my rank, or
promotion. That was not on I was not
interested in that. My view was always
like I I would much rather be
under-promoted than over-promoted. Um,
I'd much rather be doing work where
people are like, "Wait a minute. Why is
Wait, why why are you back here? Like,
what happened to you?" You know, I I've
I that's just
I I am not interested in being kind of
doing work performatively.
Um, I was always going to do what like
what I thought was the most important
thing to go do. Um, and you know, Sun
was a company that was very
accommodating of headstrong engineers.
Uh, and um, so I um, that's where I I
what I wanted to do was solve the
problems that our customers had, make
the operating system
what I believed it could be, kind of
realize that vision for what the OS
could be. Um, Sun was the only company,
honestly, in 1996 that was really
invested in the operating system. Every
other company was mortgaging its future
to Microsoft and Windows. And all these
computer companies were giving up on
their own operating system, giving up on
Unix. It was really Unix's darkest hour.
And the being in that group in Solaris
kernel development during those years
was enormously energizing and allowed us
to do all sorts of things. And then
along the way you get promoted, right?
Along the way like promotions were just
the kind of thing that that happened as
you as you went along the way.
Um the I mean Sun's
I became I learned I would say I I took
a away a lot of life lessons in terms of
of what works and doesn't work. Um I
found that the because of course we had
had
formalized performance review. And I
find this is like not a deep thought,
but that formalized performance review
never resulted in me having higher
performance.
And
this is like this is one of these things
that you kind of like feels very naive
to say cuz it's like you know dummy like
performance review is not about you
performing better, it's about us
measuring your performance. It's like
well that's not what it should be about.
It what it should be about is like what
feedback is great. Like we should be
making everyone be the best that they
can possibly be. And the the the
formalized the annual cadence of it I
felt was very broken. You know, we would
have
submit a self review of course, and then
your review is like oh wow my review
looks stunningly like my self review
albeit with great grammatical errors
introduced.
Uh and
you know that it and every review um
even the reviews in which I was promoted
there was not uplifting. Like that was
not when I look back at the moments of
like what were the the the highlights
for me during that progression. It was
never being promoted. It was always
doing a significant body of work or
nailing a hard bug or working with
someone on something that we thought was
impossible. Like that was the stuff that
that that was really catalytic for me.
Um and then there's like Sun just kind
of had to promote me along the way. Now
the one exception though I would say to
that is that the
the promotion to distinguished engineer
is was very regrettable and stupid. I
mean not my promotion, but just in
general like the process. The process
for being promoted at Sun was I would
say very traditional in that you know,
you're taking your folks that are
performing very well and you're
promoting them up to the next grade. Uh
the Sun did have a very
uh
silly process thing that you know, they
had three grades they would give you
superlative, excellent, and good. And
then I think there was like a you know,
and like 70% good, maybe 20% excellent,
and 10% superlative something like that.
And they had this thing where if you
were superlative, they had to promote
you. Like that was like the index for
promoting you. Like if you got that
superlative grade, they'd promote you.
But also they had to promote you if you
they gave you that superlative grade. So
you would have I had these I had these
reviews that were like apologetic being
like, "Look,
I have to give you an excellent grade
even though like the work that you've
done over this past period has been
extraordinary and innovative and
actually better than the work that you
did 2 years ago or a year ago, but I I I
can't actually give you the superlative
grade because if I give you the
superlative grade, I would have to
promote you and we just promoted you a
year ago and it's really like we don't
want to promote people any faster than
every 18 months." And you're like,
"Okay. Does this make sense to you? I
mean this doesn't like I was like,
"Okay, if like if if you're satisfied
with this, like fortunately like I just
don't care one way or the other. So like
sounds good. Okay, can I get back to
work now? Are we are are we done here?
It's like are we And then are we getting
trying not to be trolled by the
grammatical reviews in my in in in in
the review that's being handed to me?"
Um so now the difference for that was
the And then you know, the promotion to
staff engineers was a big deal. And like
great, fine. Actually it was funny
because all the staff engineers so Sun
had this thing called KEEP, the key
employee incentive program.
And KEEP was effectively like an annual
dividend. It was like a bonus. So that
you know and there was like a keep pool
that was set across the company and
you know kind of a traditional thing,
right? And the the metric was based on
like company performance. That's what
they and so I would did hear when I was
you know an MTS3 MTS4 the staff
engineers like you know they would get
their keep bonus and if the keep bonus
is really good they take everyone out to
dinner and it was kind of like you know
it was like being at the the mining
town, right? when there's a big or
strike or what have you gold strike. So
I was like okay wow this is like this
would be great. So of course I mean just
like of course like when do I get
promoted to staff engineer must have
been in like 2000 2001. I get promoted
to staff engineer as like the dot com
nuclear bomb goes off and the keep bonus
was I never got like keep bonus was zero
from then on out. Sun lost 98% of its
value in the public markets and like I
never so it's a good thing that I wasn't
doing it for the keep bonus because the
keep bonus was was zero.
Um
but then getting so that was staff
engineer to senior staff engineer and
then distinguished engineer what is was
really unfortunate in that there were
there were kind of two paths in to
distinguished engineer. And this may be
true of of a lot of companies I don't
know. I mean I have we I don't have
ranks at Oxide for this reason like I
think ranks are corrosive. I don't think
they get people to do their best work
I'm not interested in them. Um but the
at Sun there were two ways to be a
distinguished engineer. One was of
course to be like promoted from a senior
staff engineer to distinguished engineer
and that was a very very I mean I would
say rigorous but it's giving it far too
much credit. It was very political
process. The DEs would vote on whether
you should be admitted to this country
club of distinguished engineers which is
a terrible idea. Putting like this is
like the wrong place for democracy in a
society right the for so many different
reasons. And the but so that's how you
would get promoted to distinguished
engineer. Very hard to get promoted. The
other way to become a distinguished
engineer is Sun is buying your little
company. Is Aqua hiring your company?
And your the company's got just enough
leverage during that process to be like,
oh by the way, our CTO needs to be a DE.
So, you would have these like DEs just
kind of like pop in the side. You're
like, who is this person? Like, oh yeah,
we yeah, then we acquired their company.
So, and and there was definitely a
difference in like you you knew the the
homegrown DEs versus the ones that had
been had been aqua-hired in. Um but when
I and I I actually like and this is like
I just do not want to even think about
this process. Like again, I'm not a real
political person. Like the last thing I
want to do. Uh fortunately, we had um I
I'd done work that was kind of so
indisputable at that point that it was
going to be um it was pretty clear that
if Sun is going to have such a rank, I
was probably worthy of it. But again, I
didn't want to deal with it. Uh Sun's
CTO at the time, Greg Papadopoulos, very
grateful to Greg. Um Greg had chartered
this group that we'd developed um inside
as actually in San Francisco for Sun
mission called Fishworks where we had
developed a new storage product. Uh
storage product was going gangbusters.
Um it was a great product. Uh although a
great product with asterisks on it.
Wasn't as great as we thought it was. We
should have that. We learned a lot about
it. Um
but the product was doing really well.
Uh Greg Again, I was not in the meeting,
so this was told to me secondhand. Um
but uh your DE case needs to be
presented by someone, another DE. Well,
Greg presented my case. And so, you had
the CTO of the company and Sun was not a
very hierarchical company and Greg was
not a very hierarchical person. But Greg
put apparently my materials up and it's
like, I don't expect anyone to vote
against this. Take your vote. He said
that? Yeah. And apparently it was
unanimous. So, it's like, thank you,
Greg. Um deeply appreciate it. So, Greg,
I didn't have to deal with that
because uh Greg was dealing with it for
me. Um and it was kind of like, you
know, honestly, it was kind of a
validation of my hypothesis. Like, Greg
honestly viewed it more of a reflection
on the company than a reflection on me.
It's like, great. I had done work that
was at some level kind of indisputable
and that's kind of the way I I had
wanted to chart my career. I I think
there's two schools of thoughts on on,
you know, how people structure their
careers within these, I guess, ladders.
If a really ambitious new graduate
engineer comes to you and say, "Hey, I
want to be a distinguished engineer one
day."
I have two ideas. One idea is I'm going
to just focus on the work and just, you
know, promotions will be a byproduct. Or
I'm going to do the other thing where
Yeah, I talk to my manager. I'm like,
"Hey, how do I get to that next level?"
And "Hey, what are those things that the
next level needs to do?" And then I will
do work that molds to that mold.
Yeah, I would try to to steer someone
with a third path. What's the third
path?
>> Like, what Why? Why do you want to be
What What is it Why do you want to be a
distinguished engineer? Because
if that's the goal, if the goal is to be
a distinguished engineer, you you get
there. You'll be a distinguished
engineer. Now what?
I mean, you
you
you can be so fixated on that. It's like
it doesn't at some level it doesn't that
doesn't actually That's not the thing
that matters. That's That doesn't give
you meaning.
And to me, if I had a young engineer
who's like, "I'm I want to be a
distinguished engineer." I'm like,
"That's a recipe for a midlife crisis."
So, what what the what the what What's
try to dial you differently.
And I think that what I think what you
would what I would steer someone to is
What What's get you on a path that has
meaning, where you're going to be
developing, and what drives meaning for
you. What's important to you? And it's
like, "Well, what's What's important to
me is to be a distinguished engineer."
I'll be like, "Okay."
I mean, you you'd want to tease it
apart. Get them on the couch a little
bit. Like, why I mean, are you not Were
you not loved enough as a child? Like,
what's going on? Like, you know, you
And and you know, kind of work through
some of these issues because you don't
want to be dependent on that kind of
external validation.
You I would want to be like, "Let let
introduce you to people who've achieved
what you are putatively setting out as
your goal and are miserable. Like, let
me introduce you to some miserable D's.
You want to be wealthy? Let me introduce
you to some miserable wealthy people.
So, you know that it's like that's
that can't be it. It's
there's got to be something else that
that is that the fuel in that furnace.
And like, let's go find that thing. And
and and then we then then the like the
promotions will happen and the work will
happen.
Okay, but let's say okay, mente comes to
you and says
you have a good point. I want financial
independence. A lot of people I think
want that. Is they
they want to Yeah, what's financial
independence though? Because like we are
in such a well-compensated domain. It's
like you and I right now could go out
and get a cup of coffee
that is the best cup of coffee in the
We're in San Francisco, we're in the
mission.
We can get some coffee that is like some
Ethiopian coffee, some amazing coffee
that is like club and that is attainable
to you and me and and to basically
everyone else. It's like a $6 cup of
coffee.
Right? Yeah, yeah. Well, okay. Well,
let's say you define it as, you don't
need to work for money ever again.
But then what?
I I mean, this is like okay, you don't
need to work for money ever again. Like,
okay, I get that. But but so you can go
off and do the thing that actually
motivates you. Well, then go off and do
the thing that actually motivates you.
What if it doesn't make money? Well, I
think it and I
Well, this is where I you want to take
it apart. And so like you want to find a
way I mean, certainly you're going to
have things like
the the the the difference that you want
to make, the meaning that you're going
to find is going to be something that's
like, yeah, this is this is just not a
career path at all. Like, I can't
actually sustain myself at all. So, then
you need to find a way to balance that,
I would say, with your career.
And you want to keep that balanced. I
think it I also think it's a mistake to
be like, I'm going to achieve financial
independence and then I'm going to do
the thing that is meaningful to me. It's
like And again, you just And I I
definitely had the blessing of know Most
people were like me. Made a lot of money
on paper in the dot com boom and just
lost every penny of it. I mean, I had a
I had a loss carry forward for so many
years that I actually like One year I
lost track of my loss carry forward. I'm
like, "I got to I I just So But I had a
loss carry forward I that And I was
like, "You know, I had like fun memories
of the dot com bubble when I would take
my whatever it was, $3,000 a year
against my from a loss carry forward."
Um the That was most people around here.
Most people kind of like
lost it all, but also were fine. And I
think this is the other thing. Like the
dot com bust was super helpful because
if you had geared yourself to be really
economically motivated
in '99, 2000, '98, '99, 2000, which
would have been easy.
2001, 2002, 2003, like you That was not
why you were here.
Because this place was nuclear winter.
And And you had had to find something
else. And I I knew like So the funny
thing I knew like lots of people that
like had to remind themselves why they
got in this, and it wasn't money. I also
knew people I didn't know people that
made a bunch of money in the dot com
boom. The people that made a bunch of
money in the dot com boom weren't that
interested in tech to begin with. So
when it went up in, you know, late '99,
2000, they're like, "I'm selling it all.
Like I actually don't want to do this."
And those people, and there are a couple
of them that I know, and some of them
really really struggled in the next
decade cuz they didn't have to work for
the rest of their lives. But now what?
Like you don't have to work, so like now
what do you do? And And they were on
their own search for meaning. And like
not easy. And going through periods of
like, "Oh, like I'll buy six houses."
Then you realize like six houses are
kind of like a pain in the ass. It's
like you and I could go drink six cups
of coffee concurrently, but you're just
like, "What am I doing here? Am I just
like proving that I can buy six cups of
So like why do I want six houses? All
right, then I then I then you you scale
that way back. I mean, it gives you like
it really opens your eyes about what
matters and what doesn't matter. What
doesn't matter as much. Certainly, you
need to be able to provide for yourself
and provide for for a family. You want
to be able to raise a family and so on.
So, you want to be able to have that
But, you want to do that in a way that's
honestly sustainable. I think that that
too many folks are focused on like, I'm
going to do this so I can leave. It's
like,
then maybe you shouldn't be in this
industry at all. Like, go do It's like,
go do the thing you would do when you
left and find a way to do that in a way
like and go pursue that dream. And cuz
you'll be you'll be happier. You'll
you'll have meaning doing that. Quit
your job at Meta and become a podcaster,
you know?
>> Oh, well, I did Yeah, [laughter] yeah,
yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah,
yeah, exactly.
Well, um
yeah, it's it's uh it's interesting you
say that because there's this um
there's this subreddit, this community
that's all about uh financial
independence, earning enough, and
>> Yeah. Oh, Jesus.
>> see a a very regular post that says,
"Guys, I did it and I don't know what to
do now."
>> Oh, yeah, exactly. [laughter]
Yeah.
Yeah. I did it. I did And also like I
geared I mean, I think this is like this
is a problem, by the way, in
engineering, not even in the
even when the goal was has meaning, this
is a problem. This is what I This is
what I call postpartum in engineering.
you are really focused on shipping
something and you're just like,
"Shipping this thing is just the lens
through which you're doing everything."
And when we shipped our first rocket
oxide, I was very concerned about like,
"We are going to have postpartum." And
there are going to be people who are
like, "I was working so hard and pulling
so hard for so long and now we shipped
it and like, now what?" And I'm I So,
even when the thing you've done is
obviously meaningful and you've achieved
something extraordinary, you're going to
have that. When the thing you've also
achieved is like, "Well, I can like buy
any cup of coffee I want." It's like,
"The thing I want like now I'm not even
sure I got I got like what am I supposed
to do?" I
it's just easy to see
how you people be wonder what the
meaning of it really is. And then there
are some people that are just like snip
all the wires and they're like, well,
the meaning of it is to get even more.
And then just like, you know,
then you get like Larry Ellison or
whatever. But like
that's also not something that people
should aspire to. Right. I Well, what
would you say cuz I I do know someone
who is genuinely happy
just doing nothing.
By doing nothing, I just mean like
relaxing in bed, you know, watching
their shows, you know, going to hanging
out with friends and stuff. I think if
they had a billion dollars, they'd just
do that every day. Yeah. But what you
said doesn't work in that case cuz that
doesn't earn anything. I you know, I
actually did know a guy I knew a guy who
I actually did know a guy who did this
who I was I'm thinking about people who
made money that I know
I knew one of
I I believe one of Yahoo's like first
employees, but not because he was like
crazy sharp or anything. Because he like
they they wanted to hire a web surfer
and he was like a pothead who was like
this like this sounds like the level of
work that I'm a So, he gets a job as
like a web surfer one at Yahoo, but as
like employee number like single digit.
He gets the equity grant as part of like
joining the company. Never gets another
equity grant, but makes a king's ransom
because he's very early at Yahoo.
Never promoted above like web server
rank one or whatever and was complaining
to everybody about how much his job
sucked. Everyone was like, you surf the
web for a living. Like you've somehow
managed to like win this insane lottery
where you're getting paid to do like
very close to nothing. And he like at
when it started, he owned like all of
Yahoo in terms of like surfing. Cuz the
way Yahoo worked, you you may be
wondering what the hell I'm even talking
about. Yahoo was a curated directory of
links. Like this is again where I sound
like a pre-Google.
Very much pre-Google. This is like
pre-Google This is not just pretty
Google. This is like pre-Lycos,
pre-Hotbot, pre-Altavista. This is This
is like basically pre the ability to
search the internet.
You would have these curated directory
of links. And someone needs to go like
find this content. And it was like this
guy, Yahoo employee number six or
whatever he was.
And so he originally like owned the
entire directory, but he's like not very
good and not very energetic and was
like, you know, stoned all the time. So
they kind of like carved It's a Finally
he I I believe at the end, before he
finally quit, he owned only like
snowboarding in northern California.
That's what it was his like
responsibility
to It's like, this is a job? And
So that is the kind of person who was
And you would like to think that that he
found something that was actually
meaningful to him, but clearly it was
not the work or work for that matter.
Right. Um You said earlier there were
these ratings was superlative excellent
and
>> something like that. Yeah, yeah, yeah. I
noticed you didn't mention there's
there's a bad rating or something.
>> Right. There was a Yeah, no, there were
there was not Basically not. Sun did not
um the the idea of like a PIP or the
whole like rank and yank, which is what
Intel famously did.
Um the Rank and yank? The rank and yank.
Is that Is that just stack ranking and
firing people?
>> was It was their name for stack ranking.
Yeah. It was It was It was rank and
yank. Um
yeah, stack rank Stack ranking is
organizational cancer. It is It is very,
very, very bad news. When you especially
if you are going to terminate a bottom
end percent, that is um that's death. I
I I really think that is just a a
wall-to-wall terrible idea because you
incentivize people to have dead weight
on their teams um that they can that Oh,
is that Oh, so they have fodder to
>> someone to throw into the wood chipper.
Oh, wait, so you think that a manager
strategically keeping around
>> Oh, I know so. I mean that definitely
happened at Sun, for sure. Oh, yeah, for
sure. I mean there were people that were
like, why are they still here? Like they
don't They don't know what they seem to
be doing anything. And someone kind of
took me aside and was like, "Yeah, that
person is in your best interest because
like do you know what that person's
rating is? It is always like good."
Like they they get a good so you can be
an excellent or a superlative. And I'm
again, I'm like, "Does this make sense
to you? Like why are we okay?"
So you know all sorts of perverse
incentives. All sorts of perverse
incentives with with stack ranking. Was
that stack ranking fundamentally you
that stack ranking teaches you that your
team are adversaries.
And
that's a bad idea. That is and it's just
not the way I want to operate. Like they
the my big belief is that that teams do
extraordinary things.
And that everybody should want to be
serving the team. It is it is the team
that wins or loses. The team that
succeeds. And I I think that stack
ranking really operates very much
contrary to that. You mentioned that
Sun
I mean the stock stock price went down
by 98% Yeah, yeah. Trading below our
cash at one point.
>> I mean was there not some management at
some point saying, "Hey, we got to
it's time to Oh, we did I mean mass
layoffs
>> no. Sun did I mean Sun resisted layoffs
for a little while. Scott was kind of
famously did not McNealy famously did
not want to lay people off but that was
which was a mistake. He waited too long
for that. Um but no, once the layoff
started I mean I think at one point I
counted the the number of layoffs that
had the rounds layoffs was like 35
layoffs. 35 rounds of layoffs over like
eight years.
That's I mean it's more than four a
year.
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, absolutely.
Yeah, no, it was it was brutal. That's
that's insane.
>> And well, you get these like small
layoffs, big layoffs. I mean this is
actually before the Warn Act, I think.
Um but you would get We actually I mean
this is dark. But we you could you could
There was an API effectively to the
well, well, this is like before the era
of rest APIs, but
there was a way to get the employee
directory programmatically. And so, we
would run what we called the obits, and
the obits would run every day and would
tell you who was no longer at the
company. And so, you would see these
small layoffs that were not actually
like you you would see, you know, a
group that was like or you would see and
then you would see like, "Oh my god,
like that's 1,500 people or that's 3,000
in today's obits."
Was the company aware that you had that
access to that data?
That seems like Sun you
Sun's strength and weakness was that no
one was truly in charge. So, I mean, I
think it would not have been I would not
have been surprising.
But, I mean, Sun to its credit was a
pretty transparent company. So, I don't
think that we would have I think that we
weren't violating any kind of policy. We
were accessing a we were accessing the
org tool, which was the tool they had to
show you kind of organizational layout.
So, we weren't doing anything untoward,
but it was a way for us to know like
what's happening in the company as the
Sun had was layoff after layoff after
layoff after layoff after layoff. That I
mean, 35 layoffs that's
almost yeah, that's crazy. I um
>> But, that was everybody, too. Again,
that was not like
oh like
the it is hard to express the period
from the dot-com bust when you know,
kind of pets.com craters in in the
spring of 2000 that kind of ran on on
momentum until the end of 2000. And at
the end of 2000, the dot-com bubble
truly truly burst for everybody
for Sun included.
And then
and 9/11 did not help, right? So,
what was and the economy was tech was
basically dead for five years.
And and Y Combinator is formed kind of
at that Y Combinator is I think 2006.
I see.
And starts to form and I think in part
because I think you know, you have to
take Graham's perspective on this, but
but the
I mean
there was a there was a capital deficit
at that point. There were like people
that could solve interesting things and
there was like no way to start a company
to go do it. Um so the it was really
really bleak here for many many years. I
see. Slightly off topic, but I I was
stalking your Twitter and I saw that
Paul Graham had blocked you. Do you know
is Oh, Paul Graham blocked me. He didn't
block me. I think he Yeah, that was a
point of pride. I I did feel like I felt
like I'd really arrived when Paul Graham
blocked me. Yeah, Paul Graham blocked
me. Yeah, I definitely feel like I'm I'm
on the right side of history on that
one. Um Well, what do you think that was
for? Uh no, I know what that was for. Um
that was for um I think that uh Paul
Graham was
uh defending some of the worst behavior
of Richard Stallman. And the worst
behavior of Richard Stallman does not
age very well. It's truly truly uh some
pretty gross kind of behavior.
Uh and he was defending that and I was
attacking him for it and he was blocking
me for that. So like, all right. Uh I'll
take that. Um
Yeah, I mean Paul Graham is complicated
for me. He uh there were there are a
couple of people like this in Silicon
Valley that are complicated in that
there are uh says some things that I
really strongly agree with and some
things that I really strongly disagree
with. Um often in the same sentence. So
often and you're just like like my
brain's getting zapped. Like, okay, this
is like wrong but also not wrong and uh
so Um yeah, he's he's he's he's a
complicated one. There are a couple of
people like that.
I understand that Sun Microsystems was
eventually acquired by Oracle. Yes,
invaded. Yeah. And uh I just want to
know why was it so controversial at the
time? There's even a Wikipedia page that
says the acquisition of Sun Microsystems
and there's it's almost like an obituary
and there's
a lot of top level engineers who Um
well, it was
it was traumatic.
Um there's actually a really interesting
SEC filing because it's a public company
that IBM and HP were both jockeying to
try to buy Sun. And each was trying to
sabotage the other and each was trying
to get the kind of
because they almost wanted to buy Sun
punitively. They were both competitors
with Sun. Um and while they were kind of
screwing with one another, Oracle swept
in and bought the company.
Um so um
Oracle that happened really quickly. Um
the actual acquisition itself was not
really controversial. It took a while to
close. Um what what I mean to
to the contrary, I mean there's nothing
like really controversial about Oracle
because Oracle is what it is. Um Oracle
is just there's not a lot of depth to
Oracle. Um Oracle is just an octopus
that knows how to feed itself and the
um
the Sun was very much not that way. Sun
was there was a there was a level I
wouldn't call purism, but there was Sun
was always endeavoring to do the right
thing by its customers. Sun was
endeavoring to to solve hard interesting
technical problems that had commercial
relevance and
it gave its engineers us tremendous
freedom to go do so. And and it tended
to do attract people that wanted to to
do that that wanted to do that was
wanted to be bold and
it was it was a great place for that
reason because it rewarded that kind of
technical boldness. So that's why you
know
and if I had Spark and Java and and
Solaris and all the technologies that I
worked on, you know, all these things
came out of Sun. There were so many of
these like seminal technologies that
came out of Sun because of
of that kind of that passion and
independence. Oracle doesn't have any of
that. Oracle's just like
Oracle it truly is is focused on really
on on one thing, namely its own
profitability which is like I thought
what when the acquisition happened I'm
like well this will be interesting cuz
we'll get someone with like great
business savvy maybe. One of the things
that was frustrating me about Sun is
that Sun um on terms of business
execution, Sun fell down a bunch of
times. And I thought we would have
someone in Oracle that would be just
better at the execution of a commercial
enterprise. Uh as it turns out, I was
really overestimating Oracle. Um Oracle
really is about um
being able to to get effectively a
monopoly, a natural monopoly over its
own customers, asphyxiating competition,
and then raising the rent on its
customers. Like that is really what
Oracle wanted to go do. Um and it's not
a company I wanted to work for.
I see. Because I had there's a talk that
you gave that where you really uh I
mean, you know, I didn't even Yeah, I
know you're talking about The the talk
is crazy.
>> the Lisa talk from 2011. Yeah, before
you even got to talking about it, you
said, "I'm going to try and make it
through this slide without crying." Oh,
that was on the the the Sun side.
>> Yeah, yeah. And then I think you were
talking about Oracle and you said that
they screw customers and lie. I guess
you explained the screw customers part,
but what's the lie part of of Oracle?
>> Yeah. Oracle is
um has made many promises to its own
customers that it does not keep. Oracle
does not has not earned the trust of its
customers. If you ask customers, "Do you
trust Oracle?" the answer to that will
be no.
And I would kind of let that speak for
itself. Um the yeah, the the making that
slide without crying bit was not about
Oracle, that was about very much about
Sun.
Um and that was the and the the I
Scott McNealy's
epitaph for Sun. Kick butt, had fun,
didn't she? Loved her customers, changed
computing forever.
>> Yeah, you said that. Yeah, yeah.
>> Yeah, that was the bit that And like it
still chokes me up a little bit just
because
it it's true. It was true. And we um
when we started Oxide, we like adopted
that as our own mission because that
that's It's what we wanted to go do at
Oxide.
Um and I thought it was a very uh
concise distillation of that. And that
was just not Oracle. Oracle's not
interested in that. Um When when a lot
of the top engineers it seems like there
was a an exodus where
>> exodus, yeah, yeah. where people
confiding with each other like were you
talking to other high-level engineers
saying, "Hey, we got to get out of
here." Oh, yo, yeah. I mean, it's not
even like I mean, you're just like
you're in a burning building. Are people
confiding with one another they should
leave the burning building? It's like,
"No, actually people are just like
running for their lives." I mean, you're
just not like, "Oh, what do you think of
the burning building? Like do you think
the building is burning? What do you"
Uh and no, I mean, it was pretty clear.
And there were actually the real true
jockeying came from those engineers
before it actually closed. There were
going to be some engineers that would be
laid off
before it closed.
But as the acquisition closed, in other
words, there were some people that were
still employees that were not going to
be Oracle employees. Uh Aqua laid off?
Like they wouldn't There wouldn't be a
existing company.
>> They just That's right. So so that they
would they would lose their job. Okay,
okay.
>> But they would get like a pretty rich
severance package.
So you had like an absolute line at the
trough for how can I get laid off? You
[laughter] like I I lay me off first. Um
this was not me. This was not us. We
were I I
I was I mean, in I mean, at least to the
credit of the like the people lining up
at the trough, at least they knew what
was going to happen. Uh [snorts] and
there were still people to this day that
are a little resentful. People are like,
"That guy uh
That guy got laid off and I I mean, I
quit because I could not work there in
good conscience after 45 days. That guy
got laid off and got a year of salary or
whatever it was." Um but we No, I um
I was not that. I was We were at this
Fishworks group in San Francisco and I
was really optimistic that I'm really
optimistic, somewhat optimistic um that
we could combine the best of both
companies or what I perceived to be the
best of both companies. And as turns
out, that's not the case. So. What did
you see cuz you left really quick? So
what did you see then?
>> Oh, it was really clear to me that that
this was a very very different company.
I mean, Oracle gave me like I had
decided like I can't work here anymore
and the time between I had decided that
and I actually left, which was only like
30 days, more a little longer than that,
maybe 45 days.
Oracle gave me like four other reasons
to be like, oh my god, I just can't I
can't stomach working here. I mean, I
and I mean, it was a bunch of things.
One, it was Sun for all of its faults
and there were many many faults of Sun,
Sun had the trust of its customers. Our
customers actually were rooting for us
at Sun. Our customers wanted us to
prevail. Why? Because they actually they
they trusted us and they even when it
wasn't in our own best interests. Like
we would we would be straight with our
customers and I think that that was we
did not lie to our customers, right? And
that was something that our customers
found very very appealing. That was not
Oracle. Oracle does not have the trust
of its customers and I realized
something very important about myself. I
can't work for a company that has that
kind of profound distrust. I mean, in
terms of what we're talking about
meaning, that so eroded my own sense of
meaning. I felt ashamed. I felt ashamed
to work there and I had never felt that.
I've never, you know,
for Sun, I was embarrassed from time to
time, but never ashamed and with Oracle,
I was ashamed. Uh you mentioned people
were were eager to get themselves laid
off.
How do you even
How do you even do that? Just like say
>> your manager, look, there's a list, put
me on it.
Yeah, oh, there is a list? Okay, who
else is on it? Like I want to be on it.
I mean, just like all the ways that you
I mean, it's not like you don't fill out
a web form. I mean, you're obviously
like it, you know, you're
you're a courtier kind of whispering
about trying to figure out like what's
the scuttlebutt, who's going to get laid
off.
>> Uh I thought you'd have to like really,
you know, underperform and like
>> No, no, no, no, no one said no, no. I I
think that they were no, it was all
about like hey, I I'm I I have no value
to Oracle. Could you I mean it was much
more like [laughter] Oracle's not
interested in what I'm doing, right? And
then you get like Oracle is interested
you got to god damn it.
Um [snorts]
Uh so okay, so I I get why you left
Oracle and and obviously Sun was
acquired. And so I the next place you
worked at was Joyent. And I understand
that
this company competed with AWS. That's
right, yeah. And uh I listened to some
of the conversation you already had and
yeah, interesting quote. You said Bezos
is the apex predator of capitalism.
Yeah.
What makes you say that? Very they're
just Amazon was Amazon at its height
was such so relentless on execution.
And what made Bezos
really, really good is that in and I
would say like and when I say it's
height, I mean they Amazon hits the
mother lode. And they they they hit the
mother lode
not because they're lucky. But they they
there there was like luck involved, you
know, they they allow S3 to be
developed, right? They develop EC2. Then
they they realize what they're on to.
And they're on cloud computing before
anyone has figured it out. And the the
the the those reinvents in like from
to say 2015
were relentless. Every reinvent was a
price cut. It was price cut and it was a
bunch of new services.
And if you're a customer, you're like
this is awesome. I love this. This is
great. Like why would I not I mean so it
was so that's what I mean by the apex
predator because he was on something
that was wildly profitable.
He pulled off a just an absolute
move of moves in that Amazon did not
break out their revenue.
So it's just like Amazon. It's like you
got the dot com side, you have AWS.
They're not breaking out any of that.
They're just like literally like this is
how much Amazon's making. Analysts would
ask in the call, they're just like,
"Yeah, we're not talking about that."
Which apparently you can get away with
as a public company.
Um and so, they actually created this
idea, especially with the relentless
price cuts. People are like, "Oh, the
cloud's a terrible business." Like no
one no one should get into the cloud
because it's a terrible business.
And so, people didn't. And meanwhile,
like what we knew because we did compete
with Amazon, we did have a public cloud,
and we knew it's like, "No, the actually
the margins on this thing are great."
Like this is actually a great business.
And Amazon And Amazon was executing
very, very, very, very well. And they
did extraordinarily well in the in in
those years. And I mean, they are still
obviously it's a it's a it's a very
profitable company, but they have Amazon
has it is not what it was in in those
years. Um
I'm not sure when the last price cut was
announced at re:Invent, but it's been a
while.
Um it is not that that's not what you
get at re:Invent. You don't get the the
kind of the new services that you can't
live without. Um so, it's it's a
different company.
AWS was was early, and they already had,
I guess, a dominant market share.
>> Yeah. Why would Jeff Bezos continue to
just
like ruthlessly keep going and keep
going? And because instead of milking
it, Because he is not merely a predator.
He is an apex predator in capitalism.
This is what makes him so good. He's
like, "I'm not going to No, like I'm
going to I'm going to press my
advantage."
Like I'm I'm going to make it so no one
can compete with me.
And I'm going to make it so no one wants
to get into this business. And I'm going
to do it Honestly, like the right way.
I'm going to do it by like giving a
great product at a reasonable price.
It's like, "Damn, yeah, that's that's
good. That's like that's how That's a
win-win." That's a win-win, and it was
like essential for innovation during
that era of companies that were
cloud-born.
And it I mean, it was really I it was
very, very hard to compete with Amazon.
I'll tell you that. You had to you had
to really like find a lane. And we know
we we found lanes where we could go
compete with Amazon, but it was uh it
was it was brutal. They There were There
execution was extraordinary.
At this company, I I saw that you you
started out as a VP and then you
transitioned to CTO at some point. And
>> Yeah. What's the difference in the
roles?
>> Was it That's a great question. I
actually gave a talk on this with
Joyent's CTO at the time on the contrast
between VP of engineering and CTO. Um
and you know, I'm not sure
how much I
how much I buy the difference now. I
mean, I think both in both capacities
you're serving as an engineering leader.
Um and I I think that you know, I guess
you can argue that a CTO is more
outward-looking for sure. Chief Travel
Officer is kind of the the the the
pejorative for it. You're on the road
talking to customers a lot. Um you are
um a VP of engineering may be more
focused on some of of the necessary like
mechanics that you have in an
engineering organization. Um for me
personally, I mean, they brought me in
as a VP of engineering because they
frankly already had a CTO. So like I
again, it's just like the the the grade
I was at uh
at Sun, I didn't particularly care. What
I did care about is when the, you know,
the CTO had left and then another CTO
that we had the CTO who had been a
founder of the company. And when he
left, uh so there was kind of like the
the
the empty CTO position.
I didn't care What I did care was that
we didn't hire externally for that
because I So that I did care about a lot
about. Like, look, if there's going to
be a CTO, I'm happy to be VP of
engineering in perpetuity. But like I
would rather like if there's going to be
a CTO, I would like us to not hire
externally for that, please. Or let me
be involved in that anyway. But um yeah,
I was later the CTO. And why not hire
externally? I just didn't want to deal
with like having to bring in I didn't
need That's not what we needed at that
time. What what we needed um at at that
time especially, well, we had we got rid
of the CEO um and we we really were um
we we needed
really a terrific CEO, which we which we
later got. So.
And so then you started Oxide. Started
Oxide in 2019. Yeah.
>> And what's the story behind you starting
your own company?
Well, I knew again I I kind of
had in my I my mind that like I want to
start a company. And the thing that I
knew is I want to start a company with
Steve.
Steve and I had worked together at that
point.
Steve was the when I went to Joyent I
not talked to Steve prior to going to
Joyent. And I was going to Joyent in
part because I was running away from
Oracle and it was a it I it was kind of
allow me to to hire folks and so on.
But the I didn't talk to Steve until
after I came to Joyent. And I'm like
this guy is amazing. And Steve and I
just worked very closely together. Steve
came up on the go to market side on the
sales side. And
I knew I'm like I definitely want to
start a company with this guy. I and and
he fortunately he felt the same. So we
we both felt like all right, whatever we
do next we do it together.
Um And so now it's like all right, well
now what? Now we got to figure out what
we want to go do. And we had these long
walks in the city cuz we're working in
San Francisco and we had so many bad
ideas. I mean it was just it was just
basically one bad idea after another. So
then we're trying to come up with ideas
that like were a better match for the
kinds of things that people would fund.
And we recommend people not do this.
It's understandable. I did it. I don't I
understand. But we're we're trying to
like come up with things that people
would fund.
And coming up with things that were just
like not in our heart. You know what I
mean? Like this is like okay, I can do
this but like really? I mean it'd be fun
to do it with Steve but just doesn't
feel like that's not going to I want to
do something that is like that is this
next long chapter of my career.
And so as we're kind of struggling with
that and I was trying to figure out like
okay, we actually need to start talking
to venture capitalists at some point. We
need to like start like get this ball
rolling and understand like I
and I had always known venture
capitalists and I got lunch with them
over the years but had not really like
you know kind of gone deep. And I know
the venture capitalists associated with
with Joyent for sure.
Um and so I got uh I was reminding
myself of the email address of one VC in
particular. Actually very famous VC.
And but it's someone I had known since
early early early in his career. And he
and I just gotten lunch periodically
through our careers from when he was
first in venture and I was in insuring
and we it's like and he had kind of
become uh become pretty famous. And I
was just want to remind myself of the
email address. And the last email he had
sent to me was just maybe you know 18
months prior was like, "Hey Brian,
really enjoy getting lunch with you
today. I just want to remind you I will
fund literally anything you put in front
of me."
I'm thinking like,
"Wow."
And I was like, "Steve, you know,
I'm reminding myself of this email of
this guy's email address. He said
he will fund literally anything we put
in front of him."
So like,
what what we should just go big. We
should do we should do the thing that is
in our heart."
And Steve's like, "What do you mean?"
I'm like, "We should build the computer
that we want to build. We should build a
rack-scale machine."
And he's like, "You got to be amazing."
Like,
"Do you think we can get that funded?"
And I'm like, I yeah I get yeah I think
so.
And you know that was very much in our
heart. That was what we had lived that
he had lived that Steve had been at at
Dell prior to Joyent. Um he'd been at at
Dell for a decade. I'd been at obviously
at Sun for for 14 years. We and then
together at Joyent for another decade.
And this is we
this was truly in our marrow.
Um
and we felt like, "Okay, like we can
go." And we as we started talking to VCs
about this about building and we again
envisioned rack-scale design. We wanted
to do our our our own board design, do
our own switch, do our
DC bus bar business line, do all of our
own software, do build the machine that
we ourselves wish we could have had at
Samsung. After Samsung acquired Join.
And what was very catalyzing actually
was going to, you know, you were what
would have been Facebook at the time
before they renamed it. And going to
their open compute going to the open
compute summit and and looking at like
Tioga Pass.
And you're like, what is this? Like
Tioga Pass like I mean it was like I
would liken it to discovering Unix as an
undergrad when I'd been living with DOS
and be like, what is this? And you go
look at Tioga Pass you're like, this is
a like this is what a computer can be?
Like this is gorgeous. This is amazing.
We got to go build this for the
enterprise market.
And we what we discovered is this was
very contrarian.
Um
but things that are contrarian are
attractive to ventures. So we would get
this into where people would actually be
pretty interested in it. Um and I I mean
you don't have to tell you how the story
ends, but we went back we had actually
talked to a bunch of venture capitalists
before I went back to that same VC that
sent me the email. And I get maybe 45
seconds into describing the problem we
want to go solve at Oxide. He's like,
Brian, Brian, Brian, stop, stop, stop.
If you are talking about starting a
computer company, I want nothing to do
with it.
And I'm like, you know, it's funny. You
sent me an email years ago that said you
would fund literally anything I would
put in front of you. And he said,
doesn't sound like me.
I'm like, well, I've got I've got okay.
What do you want me to do with that one?
I'm like, you sent me the email. It's
like, are you is your admin writing all
of your emails? Are you like, I don't I
don't you have your kid write the email?
I I don't know what to do with that one.
Like you did send me the email. Are you
calling me a liar? I mean, and I'm like,
all right, fine. And he's like, fine.
And I we were over the phone. I go to
hang up on him. And of course like VCs
this is just like it it it's in the
animal brain, right? If you you go to
hang up on a VC, they'll be like, wait,
wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, wait,
wait, wait, wait. It's like, oh, okay.
He's like, "Wait, wait, wait, wait,
wait." So, I'm like, "Fine, got it." I I
I I I I He's like, "Wait, wait, wait,
wait, wait, wait, wait, wait."
"I'm not going to invest." And I'm like,
"I know you're not going to invest." And
I knew the reason I knew he wasn't going
to invest is he's had some big zeros
in this department. And when a VC has
had zeros in something that looks close
to what you're doing, they're like, "I
want nothing to do that again." Like,
"Nope. Nope, nope, nope, nope, nope."
Was in a bad relationship with one of
those. Don't want to do that again. And
in part in their defense, it's often
because like, "Actually, I understand
this problem a lot better. And now I
understand all the headwinds. And now I
can I mean, in some ways like you need
VCs to be and they need themselves to be
like naive at some level. Optimistic is
a be a better way of phrasing it. Where
they can like envision the world as it
could be
as opposed to getting all mired in the
way the world is. You got to be kind of
blind to the odds to a certain degree.
And I knew that he was not blind to the
odds cuz he'd had two big zeros. And so,
I knew that he was going to be like and
one zero that like looked a lot like a
like Oxide.
And so, he's like, "Look, I'm not going
to find that." I'm like, again, I knew
that.
"But I do want to help you."
Like, "Okay, it's great." And I always
tell people like when you are
VCs will ask this a lot, especially a VC
that's like where you're not a fit for
them. You're not a portfolio fit for
them, you're not a thesis fit, whatever
it is, you're not a stage fit.
If they like you, they'll be like,
"Look, I'm not going to invest, but how
can I help?" And you always want to have
an answer to that question of how you
can help. And I had an I I knew how he
could help. I had a very concrete idea.
It's like, "One of those zeros,
um I want to talk to them. I want to
talk to the I want to talk to the
founders. I want to understand
everything that went wrong."
And I did. He he's like, "Okay, that I
can do." He made the intro and it was
really, really interesting. And like the
the mistake that they that that company
had made and again, had a thesis that
looked like Oxide, but they they didn't
raise a lot of ca- they they raised kind
of arguably too little capital. They got
something working that's smaller than we
built at Oxide. Minimum viable product
at Oxide is a wreck. It's big. Took us 3
years, 3 plus years to develop. They
developed something a little bit faster,
but it was much smaller. It was
basically it you could view it as like
Nitro circa like 2013. Nitro from the
Enron acquisition at AWS. Uh it does a
lot of a lot of really important offload
for AWS. So you could view it as like
very early Nitro.
But it didn't really have a market, but
they had a customer. And they got a
customer.
And they're like
great. And the customer is happy. And
they wanted to use it in particular on
their on their active directory servers.
Great. We have product market fit.
Raised a bunch of money. Hired a huge
go-to-market team.
Problem is that customer, huge bank,
only wanted to run it on like their six
active directory servers.
So they were going to buy like quantity
six.
And this is one of the world's largest
banks. You're like uh-oh. So you're
like, how many world's largest banks are
there? Like, well, there are like
a couple of others, but like are we
going to sell like, you know, two dozen
of these things? Like we got to and they
by the time they realized that they had
a lot of mouths to feed on the on the
go-to-market side and uh they in the
that wasn't a zero. It they were
acquired, but they were acquired in a
way that left the founder extremely
bitter. Um and really felt um like he
like the VCs had pumped too much capital
in them at the wrong time. Had gotten
him to do the wrong thing.
And was then trapped at the acquiring
company and was really not happy about
it. He was also the one So I was
describing what we were doing at Oxide.
He's like, that is a suicide mission.
And I just remember writing down a
little notebook. I'm just like writing
down suicide mission. Kind of
underlining it like, okay, we're on a
suicide mission.
That's fun.
When I think of rack scale compute,
especially these days, I I think of
racks of GPUs Yeah, right. more than
CPUs.
>> Yeah. Is that something that you're
building?
>> Yeah, right. Yeah, a very reasonable
question. And when we set out, we're
like, we I mean, again, set out in 2019,
the GP GPU is was around obviously and
important, but that's not what we were
focused on. We were really focused on
general purpose compute. General purpose
compute, general purpose storage,
general purpose networking. And our
belief had always been like, that's what
we actually want there there is so much
to go build there and go differentiate
there.
And of course along the way people are
like, what about an accelerator? Like
what about an accelerator or GPU?
And the problem is that the way we want
to build systems, we want to really
build systems from first principles,
where we have components that have that
have transparency at that hardware
software interface, and we want to write
that lowest layer of software. We are
the company I mean ultimately we're
building a hardware software co-design
product, and in order to be able to do
that, you need to be able to write very
low-level software.
The problem is that's really not
compatible with Nvidia. Nvidia is a
pretty proprietary company. Executes
well, but a very proprietary company.
And what that meant is there are
effectively two doors for Oxide. One is
labeled compete with Nvidia, and the
other is labeled partner with Nvidia.
And I didn't want to do either of those
things. Have not wanted to do either of
those things. Because certainly I don't
want to compete with Nvidia.
Um and I think that that's getting more
plausible now, um but we can't partner
because we just have a very different
view of how systems should be built, and
Nvidia wants to like their view is like,
we should own the whole stack. Like
forget you, whoever you are. Um so like
okay, that's fine. We're going to be
we're going to focus on general purpose
CPU. We got plenty to do over here. The
good thing that's been interesting and a
bit surprising is that because the GPU
landscape is so
so cluttered I mean that that you've got
this very aggressive the very executing
well executing company in terms of
Nvidia. You've got a lot of competitors
around it. Um it's it's a little it's
gory, right? Over there. To get
And meanwhile on the general purpose CPU
side it's like, HP, Dell, Supermicro are
the same companies that are are doing
the same kind of junk, honestly, that
they have been doing and so we are
by our lonesomes in terms of a hardware
software product over there. So over and
over and over again, we have had people
come to Oxide that we think like no, no,
we're not a fit for you because you like
you do a lot of GPU you've got a ton of
GPUs like you company famously have a
lot of GPUs. They're no, we do have a
lot of GPUs. We also have a lot of CPU
as it turns out because the
certainly the emergent AI workloads not
just AI workloads because it's special
but certainly AI workloads but high
performance computing workloads. There's
a lot of general purpose CPU that's
attached to the special purpose compute.
You know, when you're sitting there on
chat GPT and it's surfing the web, you
got the little spinny saying it's
surfing the web. That is not a GPU
that's surfing the web. That is a CPU
that's surfing the web.
And the the CPU is really, really
important. So for us, we are more
focused than ever on the general purpose
CPU and there's a there is a ton to go
do there fortunately to get this product
to be where we believe it can be and I
think we will do an accelerator at some
point but you know, I've been kind of
saying it's like 18 months away for a
while or 18 months that we would really
start thinking about it and you know, I
again I'm I know we'll do it in the
limit
but boy, not in the foreseeable future.
We've got a lot to go do as it is.
I think coming to the end I I want to
ask you some career reflections
>> it. Kind of just all over the place type
of questions. You you wrote a tweet a
while ago. I thought it was really
interesting idea which was you you said
it would be interesting to have a
conference called in retrospect where
presenters revisit talks that they've
given prior and describe how their her
thinking has evolved since and I I
pulled a bunch of stuff that you've
I guess written or said in the past so
I'm curious if your perspective has
evolved since then so we'll go through
each of those. Sure. So first one which
is actually really famous as
when I saw it I kind of did a double
take.
So, in in 1996, as a new grad, there's
this this there I don't even know what
you used Usenet was. I had to do
research, actually. But there's a guy
who he writes this long technical
response.
>> David S. Miller. Yes, and a part of it,
too, it's it's not nice, either. It just
I saw this a line in there, it says,
"Linux is lightweight, Solaris is a
pig." Which Solaris was what I guess the
Sun was.
>> Yeah. Yes.
>> And then he writes this long thing and
you reply with just a few words. You
say, "Yeah, have you ever kissed a
girl?"
>> Yeah.
Well, first of all, I want to know the
context behind it. And then also,
knowing what you know now
>> Oh, definitely in the regret department,
if that's what that's asking. Like,
yeah, I've got very few regrets in my
career, but like you can put that one
like pretty firmly in the regret column.
>> [laughter]
>> Uh yeah, no, that that was that was and
also had no idea that this was going to
live in perpetuity. That I mean, if you
could have told me in I think 1997 is
maybe when I posted Maybe it wasn't even
Was it '96 Was it '96 or '97? Certainly
like I'm I'm like 22.
Like I'm I'm very young.
If you had told me like, "Oh, by the
way, 30 years in the future, you're
going to be asked about this." I'd be
like, "What the hell?" Like no, no,
trust me, it's like the world gets
weird, you're going to be asked about
this.
The So, it was actually a Okay, this is
I'm not defending it. I just want to be
sure that I want to be clear that like
it was a mistake.
The
I it was actually a reference to a
Saturday Night Live sketch.
So, there's an SNL sketch that is from
an era of Saturday Night Live that is
just like you can't even find the video,
but they have So, the um
they William Shatner is guest starring
on Saturday Night Live. And the skit is
that William Shatner is at a a Trekkie
convention. And the Trekkies are asking
him all of these questions. And they're
asking him questions and of course like
you should like you know in episode you
know this season in this episode you
know what what was the combination on
the safe? He's like what? I don't know
that. [clears throat] I don't know I
don't I don't know that. No why why
would I know that? Like I don't that's
not even and he's like these two people
are kind of arguing themselves and
they're asking him questions that are
like this that are all about like the
the kind of the canon of Star Trek.
And then he's like, "Hey, can I just say
something?
Get a life people. You You Have you ever
kissed a girl?" That was the that was
where they you know they do a 30 going
to John Lovitz when like Vulcaneers John
Lovitz you know
that was like lost to history. Why am I
doing this? And kind of like looks down
at himself and so like it was actually
like an obscure Saturday Night Live
reference which again like I'm not that
doesn't make it any better. Um the uh
yeah it was
that was that's definitely in the in the
regret department.
What did he say back to that or I Oh he
had a whole lot to say back back that
and I actually did have a longer post
kind of taking apart what he had said
about the about like all right like a
lot of what you've said here is actually
wrong and so like really going through
kind of point by point. I think you know
I've actually never I've never met him
never talked to him about that. He's a
very talented guy. I think he actually I
actually did read I think it was in um
the with the rebel book um about Linux
the remember him reading that he's like,
"Yeah, I kind of like was shooting my
mouth off in a sudden engineer kind of
put me in my put me back in my place."
And I'm like, "Man, if that is his read
on it he's being very generous to me."
So I'd like to believe that maybe he and
I both regretted a little bit. We were
both like a little you know a little
young and excitable um but yeah that was
definitely that was a life lesson. I
would say that history forgot about that
though.
So on another tweet
>> Yeah sorry. Yeah here we go. This is
[laughter] great.
This is we're this is like the cleanse.
Yeah.
Okay, this is in 2022 you wrote a tweet,
you said,
"If you're tempted to blame a team for a
startup's failure, please don't. Success
is often due to a great team, but
failure is almost always due to bad
leadership." I I wrote that. That's a
good one. [laughter] That's a good one.
I don't remember writing that.
That's it. I agree I agree with that
guy. He's He's on to something.
>> I guess the question is what was
something something that day on the
internet. There was some weather on the
internet that I'm sub-tweeting Paul
Graham there somewhere, I think. That
must have been it. But, um
I'm curious, do you think that's true
for for Sun? Because Sun ultimately
failed.
>> So, okay, I don't agree that Sun failed.
I don't agree that Sun failed. Because
Sun, again, Sun is founded in 1983 and
is invaded in in 2008.
2009.
That's a good run. That's a really good
run. Sun was a public company. Sun was
in the Fortune 200. Lots of people like
kids went to college because their their
parents were able to work for Sun. And
you got, you know, So, I I don't view I
do not view Sun as a failure. Sun is
like Sun did not, I mean,
arguably did not or not maybe inarguably
did not succeed to the scope of its own
ambition, but Sun to me is not a
failure. Sun is a success. Was its
collapse at the end
uh I guess
changeable in hindsight with different
leadership?
>> so. I think that there were I mean, this
is a classic power game of like why did
Sun ultimately not not survive as an
independent entity. Um and why is that?
I think there were a bunch of reasons. I
think that the
I think that there's a degree to which
Sun got very strung out on the very high
margins during the dot-com boom and
never quite like got off of that. Never
like they we embraced x86 too late. Um
we
um we kind of thought of ourselves I
mean, the the company itself became
fractured. The layoffs didn't help. I
mean, I think we at Fishworks, when we
were developing a storage appliance, I
felt that we could have been an example
of an exemplar of what the kinds of
products I felt Sun could develop and an
independent Sun could develop, but it
was going to be there's a lot of like
stuff that needed to be changed for
that. And you needed leadership that
really was very, very interested in
that. Um and it's like that just wasn't
what like that that's not what we had.
Um and in hindsight, it was probably
time for a change. So then it was And
you know, it's like it it the kind of
the way a forest fire in a normal
healthy forest fire is kind of a part of
the life cycle of a forest. And you need
that to have kind of to have to have
rebirth. And I think that that it's I
mean, ultimately, I think that that um
Sun had succeeded, but had also run its
course. And it was it was time for
>> I see. had its time. It had its time.
Absolutely had its time. Um okay. And
that next past take of yours
>> Yeah. you wrote in 2022.
Um perhaps this shouldn't have been
surprising, but Musk has absolutely no
idea what he's doing. And this is about
the takeover of Twitter and I actually
don't even know what's going on Twitter
cuz it's private at this point.
>> me. I'll I'll I will thank you to not
refer to SpaceX that way. Oh, right. It
has been acquired by XAI and then XAI
has been rolled into SpaceX. So like
we're now I guess Gwynne Shotwell now
runs runs Twitter. So I guess do do you
still agree that it's it's run poorly
and
>> Oh god, yes.
Yes. Yeah. I I agree that I mean,
because it Yeah, definitely. It's so I
mean,
yeah yes. Yes. I mean, yes. I I like I
literally feel dirty being specific
about that. But when I mean, when
there's a lot of there's rampant bad
behavior on Twitter. Um community notes,
yes. Community notes, great. Everything
else pretty much a tire fire.
What's your number one thing that is
tirefire? Um the number one thing of
tire tirefire is that they they they're
Oh, we'll tell you this. The reason that
we at Oxide don't engage on Twitter, I
can't have an Oxide tweet that is
sitting next to some of the tweets that
I've seen.
Oh, you you see Okay.
>> it's like the level of racism, the
bluntly. It I mean crazy racism, crazy
crazy racism, crazy anti-semitism, crazy
and crazy
and the anti-Islam like just
crazy hate. Crazy levels. The kinds of
things that you literally could not say
and then like oh well it's free speech.
It's like it's not free speech. It's
like it's it's so deeply offensive and
and reflected it's like
it's so deeply offensive that I don't
want my content to be anywhere near it.
I don't want someone to be looking at
that and looking at my content. I'm
sorry. I
I'm just not going to do that.
And you live through a bunch of booms
and busts and honestly I don't even know
exactly if we're in a boom or a bust
right now. It's [laughter] There's I
mean AI's going crazy and there's all
these layoffs. Crazy.
But
what what advice would you give given
your experience through the booms and
busts for people who are in today's
market?
Yeah. And I would say that some of this
I do think is endemic. I mean when I
first moved out here I'm like oh this is
great. My my grandfather was a petroleum
engineer and so I kind of grew up with
stories of like plants that were going
to be built and then shut down or
pipelines that were going to be built
and then shut down. Like everything
tracking the price of oil, right? Very
oil the oil patch is very boom and bust.
And I'm like oh this is great I'm in
software like I'm immune from booms and
busts. I remember to thinking this. Like
you know you're just like [laughter]
and
of course looking back at it now you're
like oh my god. No no we are
they are a bit endemic and they're
endemic for reasons that are are
somewhat endearing in that like we get
so optimistic that we kind of get ahead
of ourselves from an optimism
perspective. We also get ahead of
ourselves from a pessimism perspective.
And the And what I would say is like you
got to be really careful about listening
to other people.
People will tell you that this is going
to be the future or that thing is dead
and you got to be like just be your own
judge. I had people tell me that
operating systems are done in 1996.
I'm really glad I didn't listen to them.
Really glad I didn't listen to them. We
people tell us you can't start a
computer company in 2019. I'm really
glad we didn't listen to them. They you
I VC firms that say we only fund SaaS.
Those VC firms are like well it's like
SaaS is struggling right now.
Um but I would also say similarly like
if SaaS is in your heart as an example
where people are like right now people
are like SaaS is going to be the the
GenAI you the LLM assisted coding is
going to really put a squeeze on these
SaaS companies. And I think there's like
definitely truth to that. But if one's
heart is in that you should ignore the
ignore the pessimism so or or or treat
the pessimism and the optimism with a
grain of salt. Be your own judge and be
be true to what you want to do. Don't do
the things that like well I'm doing this
because it's like a hot space. It's like
you should do this because I think it's
and I'm there are plenty of people for
good reason. I mean these things are
amazing. I mean the the the the where we
are with respect to these LLMs is just
bonkers and I you could easily see how
it would be
very
find a great deal of intrinsic appeal to
that. But that's the reason that you
should be going into these systems is
because you think like no no this is
this is to to quote Steve Jobs this is
the dent I want to kick in the universe.
I notice your career almost everything's
driven from
fulfillment and intrinsic motivation.
Is there time in your career that you
look at and you say that's the happiest
time of my career? Mhm. Yeah. That's a
great question. We ask this at Oxide. We
ask you when have you been happiest and
why?
Um for exactly that reason. And I would
say that like there
it's not the it's not necessarily an
era.
Um it is it is the it is times that I've
been happy. I mean bluntly like I'm
pretty happy right now. Oxide's great.
Right? And the we have the moments for
me and this is an important kind of
question for me to reflect on as we're
starting Oxide and this is actually due
to a friend of mine who um would had
been in a startup and he and I were
taking a walk in San Francisco as kind
of Stephen and I are talking about bad
ideas
and he was like you really need to
answer for yourself why do you want to
do this? What what is drawing you to
start a company?
And cuz it wasn't financial return for
me and people should not start a company
for financial return. That's just not a
good that's not good life advice. Um but
what what was drawing me? I'm like well
the thing that's drawing me actually is
that the moments that have been the
happiest have been working on an
incredible team.
And being on a team that where everyone
individually is like I don't think we
can pull this off. Like this is actually
too difficult to pull off. And then
everybody works together, complements
one another, and you pull it off. Man,
that is a that feeling is extraordinary.
And the times that I'd have that I'd had
it with E-Tris. I I had had it at
Fishworks. I'd had it at Joyent a couple
of times with El Ax, with Triton. Um
that those times have been like oh that
that's what's amazing to me. And so I
mean in many ways like the bedrock of
Oxide is like what if we found a company
around part of the reason we were
appealing the larger problem was
appealing to us is like we're going to
be able to attract an extraordinary
team. And we have a team that is it is
so uplifting to be on a team. I've
always said that the the organizational
model for for Oxide is a heist movie.
You know, you've got your safe cracker,
you've got your getaway driver, your
demolitions expert, right? And I think
heist movies are great because of that.
And like because it's the it's the group
coming together, everyone's [snorts]
skill sets kind of coming in at exactly
the right moment. And man, I love that.
I I I love that so much and and Steve
loves it. I mean, that's that's part of
like our shared bond is he and I are
both very, very team oriented and we
built a company around that. And Isaac
is extraordinary. I It is It is truly,
truly extraordinary. It's why we've been
able to pull off what we've been able to
pull off with the small team that we've
got. I think people are kind of shocked
at how small a team that that we've got
given we've been able to pull off. You
know, when you look back on your whole
career, is there a particular top regret
that you have?
>> [laughter]
>> I mean, I made an extraordinarily bad
hire at Joyent. I think the worst hire
in human history. Many people in Silicon
Valley will say like, "Well, that can't
be the worst hire in human history
because I feel I have made the worst
hire in human history." And as I tell
people like, "Look, I'm happy to give up
the give up the crown, but you should
know that my guy presented himself under
an assumed name and just got off parole
for violent felonies from San Quentin.
And it's not what made him a bad
employee."
And usually people are like, "No, no,
no, I think you've made the worst hire
of all time." I'm like, "Thank you.
Thank you very much." Um that was a
bad experience.
It was also very eye-opening because
everything I was doing about hiring was
wrong. And we after we rectified that
situation and got him out, we stripped
hiring to the studs and really rethought
hiring from the from the very first
principles. That hiring process, a very
writing-intensive process, one that
really gets to intrinsic motivation, it
it
became the hiring process at Oxide. And
there was a moment where I'm like, "Oh
my god, like this extraordinary team at
Oxide very much
I think related absolutely to the hiring
process that we have. This hiring
process that I built because I made the
worst hiring hire time. I needed that
guy. So, you don't regret I don't regret
it. I don't I don't regret it. In fact,
I'm even like e- to kind of go back into
the time machine and remove it, I think
Oxide I don't think No, if Oxide makes
it.
Because I would have continued to hire
the way I was hiring, which was
naively.
It was hiring not rigorously. It was not
selecting people based on their values.
So, no, I absolutely needed it. So, I
think and I view that way of a lot of
things that have maybe not gone the
right way, but all of those failures
were really, really important. And it's
very hard to go back and and and you
don't want to
take those away. I mean, if I go to the
time machine, maybe I would take away
the the Usenet post and maybe that would
I don't know, maybe that wouldn't have
any long-lasting consequences, but boy,
that's about it. Awesome. And then last
question is uh if you can go back to the
beginning of your career knowing
everything you know now, what advice
would you give yourself? Jesus, don't
it up.
Don't it up. I I I I I would just
think because like I feel like so
lucky. So, I I've I've been so lucky in
so many regards. I've been in the right
place at the right time so many
different times over, and I've trusted
my gut when sometimes that was not the
thing that when
that was kind of a the contrarian thing
to do. I I mean,
I would be scared to give myself advice
because I would be worried that I would
somehow tamper with what I feel has been
an extraordinarily lucky career where I
have I I've been able to do so much with
so many extraordinary people. I've I've
I've been blessed with so many
incredible colleagues, and I
that has been so essential for
everything that I've done, and I
wouldn't want to do anything to endanger
that. So, I'd be going back to my past
self, I'd be like, I got nothing to say.
Like, just Yeah, I don't want to screw
anything up. Like, I just
because I I feel that I feel really,
really lucky. And it wasn't always
because of the because again, it's like
I I made mistakes along the way, but the
mistakes became load-bearing and
important and I wouldn't want to I
wouldn't want to not make those
mistakes. Those mistakes were really
important. Well, doesn't get better than
that and thank you for your time today.
Really appreciate it.
>> Absolutely, thank you for the thoughtful
questions. Really great conversation and
thanks for
doing the the hall of shame here on the
on the past tweets. That was a lot of
fun. Yeah.
>> [laughter]
>> Awesome. Thanks so much. Thank you.
Thank you for listening to the podcast.
It's a passion project of mine that I
really enjoyed building. Another passion
project that I've been working on kind
of in secret is building an ergonomic
keyboard that I wish existed and I
finally have a prototype. So I'd love to
show you what we've built. It's ultra
low profile and ergonomic and I couldn't
find anything like it on the market. So
that's why we built it. I'll put a link
to the keyboard in the description. You
can take a look and learn more about the
project there. We could definitely use
your support. Also, if you have any
feedback from me about the show, I'd
love to hear it. Comments on YouTube
have led to guests coming on like Ilya
Grigorik and David Fowler. I wasn't
aware of them until someone dropped a
comment. Also, feedback in the comments
helped me learn to reduce the number of
cliffhangers in the intros. So your
comments definitely make a difference.
Please keep letting me know what you'd
like to see more of in the show and I'll
see you in the next episode.